Guide to the Armand L. Mauss Papers 1952-1999
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Armand L. Mauss papers
1952-1999
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Mauss, Armand L.
Cage 854
4.0 linear feet of shelf space 8 boxes
The Armand Mauss Papers consists of research materials produced and collected by Dr. Armand Mauss, a retired Professor of Sociology and Religious Studies at Washington State University. The materials pertain to his research on student activism in the San Francisco Bay Area, mission work in Seattle’s Skid Road, and alcohol studies in Washington State, all ranging from the 1960s to the 1970s. Materials include journal and newspaper articles, survey and questionnaire data, photographs, correspondence, and miscellaneous conference files and printed materials.
Biographical Note
Dr. Armand Mauss is a Professor Emeritus of Sociology and Religious Studies at Washington State University (WSU). Dr. Mauss received his Bachelor of Arts in 1954 from Sophia University in Tokyo, Japan, and both his Master of Arts in 1957 and his Ph.D. in 1970 from the University of California, Berkeley. Dr. Mauss taught at Utah State University before joining the faculty at WSU in 1969. Dr. Mauss' earlier research focused on deviant behaviors, such as drug and alcohol abuse, but the primary focus of his classes and publications pertain to new religious movements, especially studies of Mormonism. Dr. Mauss' publications include: Social Problems as Social Movements (1975), Neither White nor Black: Mormon Scholars Encounter the Race Issue in a Universal Church (1984), The Angel and the Beehive: The Mormon Struggle with Assimilation (1994), and All Abraham’s Children: Changing Mormon Conceptions of Race and Lineage (2003). Dr. Mauss retired from WSU in 1999. While a Professor Emeritus, Dr. Mauss served as a visiting scholar for the School of Religion at Claremont Graduate University from 2004 to 2009.
This collection contains research materials of Dr. Armand Mauss on student activism in the San Francisco Bay area, Seattle’s Skid Road, and alcohol studies in Washington state. Papers pertaining to student activism in the 1960s and 1970s include articles, dissertations, conference papers and reports concerning black and white student activism and the conservative and liberal student movements. Mauss' "Skid Road" project primarily looked at the efforts of three Seattle, Washington, rescue missions: the Lutheran Compass Center, the Bread of Life Mission, and the Union Gospel Mission. Materials pertaining to this project include journal and newspapers articles, survey and questionnaire data, missions' pamphlets and reports, photographs, and correspondence. Papers related to the WSU Alcohol Studies Program from the 1970s to the early 1980s include correspondence, reports and recommendations, and research files.
The collection is arranged into four series:
Series 1: Journal of Social Issues social issue titled "The New Left and the Old," 1963-1974. This series contains correspondence, newspaper articles, conference materials, journals, papers, and publications on student activist groups. All materials in this series pertain to a special issue of the Journal of Social Issues edited by Mauss titled “The New Left and the Old.”
Series 2: Seattle Skid Road study, 1952-1999. This series contains materials produced and collected by Mauss during his study of Seattle Skid Road through Washington State University. Materials include questionnaire and survey data, materials on missions on Skid Road, correspondence, journals, newsletters, photographs, and publications on the missions on Skid Road.
Series 3: Alcohol and religion in Washington state, 1974-1995. This series contains materials by the Washington State Sociological Association, correspondence, and interview data done on the WSU Alcohol Studies program, and alcohol in Washington State.
Series 4: Published articles, 1974-1982. This series consists of publications by Armand Mauss on the topics of substance abuse and religion.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The Armand Mauss Papers were donated to Washington State University by Mauss to the Washington State University Libraries in 1997 and 1999 (MS 1997-26 and 1999-07).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Mauss, Armand L. -- Archives.
Sociologists -- Washington (State) –- Archives.; Washington State University -- Faculty –- Archives.
Civic Activism; Social Classes; Washington (State)
- Journal of Social Issues on the New Left, 1963-1974; Series 1
  - Articles and notes, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Attica uprising clippings, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Conference on students and politics in San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The New Left and the Old by Armand Mauss, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New left and student activism - large papers, 1967-1971 (Box 1-2, Folder 6-7)
  - New left and student activism - short papers, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspapers on social activism, 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Notes and bibliography, The New Left and the Old, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Political Consciousness as Reflected in the Literature of the New Left" by James L. Wood, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Radical insurgent publications, 1964-1972 (Box 2-3, Folder 11-13)
  - Right-wing student activism, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Supplemental information on Mauss, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Seattle Skid Road study, 1952-1999; Series 2
  - A Study of Man in the City, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Alcoholism programs, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Alcoholism Re-Entry Program of the Lutheran Compass Center by Armand L. Mauss and Ronald W. Fagan, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Articles on skid row, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Skid Row Missions by Reginald Wayne Bibby, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bread of Life, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bread of Life - attendance, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bibliography and observations, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Cherry Street Chapel, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Community Coordination Project Report on Survey of Seattle's Skid Road Residents, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Code guides for interviews, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Code sheets for community questionnaire, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Current Contents article, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Demographic data photocopy, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Dissertation outline, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - "The Future of the Seattle Skid Row Community" by Trevor James Evans, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - "Soap, Sleep, Soup, and Salvation" by Ronald W. Fagan, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - First Avenue Service Center, 1967-1972 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Grantsmanship techniques, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Jericho Inn Mission, Millionaire Club, Mt Carmel Chapel, Peniel Mission, and Zion Mission, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Journals and newspaper clippings on skid row, 1952-1984 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Lutheran Compass Center, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Lutheran Compass Center client intake form guides, 1973-1980 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Lutheran Compass Center correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Lutheran Compass Center evaluation report, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Lutheran Compass Center interim reports, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Lutheran Compass Center mission descriptions, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Lutheran Compass Center laity responses, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Lutheran Compass Center redraft of client intake forms, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Lutheran Compass Center rehab program, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Lutheran Ministers telephone calls, undated (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Men's street codebooks for questionnaires, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Methods in field research, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Mission attendance figures, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Missionary pamphlets, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Nepenthe newsletter on drugs and alcohol, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Newspaper clippings on Skid Road, 1974-1986 (Box Oversize)
  - Notes on street interviews, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Romance on Seattle-Skidroad, by Jennie O'Hara, undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Breath on the Mirror by Laurie Olin and bibliography on Skid Road, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Outline of the Major Points in the Lutheran Compass Center Alcoholism Resocialization Program, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Papers and outlines, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Photographs of Skid Road, undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Portland missions, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Potential studies for Skid Road rehab, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Salvation Army, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Seattle Lutheran directory, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Seattle Skid Road referral list, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Skid Road articles, 1978-1986 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Skid Road dispersion study, undated (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Skid Road Community Council, 1969-1972 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Skid Road Community Council intake forms, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Skid Road Community Council questionnaires, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Union Gospel Mission attendance, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Union Gospel Mission notes, 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Ilse J. Volinn: "Nursing on Skid Row: A Specialized Professional Role", 1999 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Ilse J. Volinn: "Skid Roads in the United States and Their World of Work", 1978 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Washington state population and "Relocating West Madison 'Skid Row' Residents" by Ronald Vanderkooi, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Washington State University faculty grant proposal, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 76)
- Alcohol and religion in Washington state, 1974-1995; Series 3
  - Alcohol Studies memo, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Collective Behavior and Social Movements, 1979-1985 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Gridded interview sheets, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Interview schedule for "The Cross and the Commune", 1974 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Washington State Sociological Association, 1977-1995 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Washington State Sociological Association newsletters, 1979-1994 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Published articles, 1974-1982; Series 4
  - "An Assessment of Needs for Dealing with Substance-Abuse Problems in Spokane County", 1977 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Evaluation Report of "Here's Looking at You" Program, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - "Prodigals as Preachers", 1974 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Spokane Youth Needs Assessment Survey, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Social Compass, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - "Teaching Religion in the Public Schools" edited by Donald H. Bishop, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 87)